Guide to the Frank Clyde Brown papers, 1912-1974 RL.00160
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frank Clyde Brown papers
1912-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Brown, Frank Clyde, 1870-1943
RL.00160
70 Linear Feet 98 manuscript boxes; 1 oversize box approximately 54,000 items
English professor, Duke University, folklorist of Durham, N.C., and founder in 1913 of the North Carolina Folklore Society. Collection centers around Frank Clyde Brown's lifelong exploration and collecting of North Carolina and Appalachian folklore, which resulted in this vast archival collection of original folklore materials and editorial records for the seven-volume Frank C. Brown Collection of North Carolina Folklore (published 1952-1964). Collection is comprised of field recordings on wax cylinders and phonodiscs; tens of thousands of field notes, transcriptions of original songs, stories, and traditional expressions; musical scores; and numerous journal articles, student theses, books, and lists. Also included are the papers of Charles Bond, a Duke graduate student who studied and expanded the collection in 1970. The vast majority of the folklore sources originated in North Carolina, but there are some materials from other regions. Subjects include: African American traditions; ballads and songs (music as well as lyrics); European roots of North American folklore; folk music; folk poetry; games and parties; oral traditions and storytelling; sayings, names, and superstitions; social conditions in the Southern States; work songs; and North American folklore in general. In addition, one can find rich resources on the study and teaching of folklore, and attitudes during the 1920s to 1950s about Southern customs and communities.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some use copies are available in the collection. Otherwise, Research Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Frank Clyde Brown papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift.
Biographical and Historical Note
Frank Clyde Brown (1870-1943) served as a Professor of English at Trinity College, Duke University, from 1909 until his death. A native of Virginia, he received his Ph.D. at the University of Chicago in 1908. While at Duke University he served in many capacities, including chairman of his department, University Marshal, and Comptroller of the University during its initial construction. These aspects of his life are chronicled in his papers held by the Duke University Archives.
This collection of materials, however, is concerned with activities to which he devoted equal time and energy, the organization of the North Carolina Folklore Society in 1913 and his personal effort to gather and record the nuances and culture of "folk" of North Carolina and its near neighbors, which occupied him from 1912 until his death. Under the impetus of a 1912 mailing from John A. Lomax, then President of the American Folklore Society, Brown as well as other faculty members and other citizens in North Carolina, became interested in folklore and organized the North Carolina Folklore Society in 1913, with Brown as secretary-treasurer. As secretary-treasurer of this organization from its inception until his death, he provided the organizational impetus behind the Society.
Through his course in folklore at Duke, he also sent class after class out to gather the folklore of their locales, both during their studies and afterward. And virtually every summer he could be found in the most remote parts of the state, with notebook and recorder -- first a dictaphone employing cylinders, and later a machine employing aluminum discs provided for his use by the University. The result, by 1943, was a vast collection of field notes, hundreds of musical scores, thousands of audio recordings, and numerous magazine articles, student theses, books, lists, and other items related to this study. The majority of the material originated in North Carolina, with the rest from 20 other states and Canada, and came from the efforts of 650 other contributors besides Brown himself.
Although Brown promised the Society on an almost yearly basis to publish at least part of this collection to which its members were contributing, he never took more than a few tentative steps toward doing so. Thus, at Brown's death in 1943, Newman Ivey White, also a Professor of English at Duke University, close colleague of Brown's, and charged by Brown with continuing the work, inherited the dual confusion of the folklore collection, which was piled in Brown's attic office at home, and the conflicting claims of ownership of the collection of Mrs. Brown, the North Carolina Folklore Society, and Duke University. When it became apparent that all were amenable to seeing the collection in print, White assumed the post of general editor, which passed to Paull Franklin Baum, also a Professor of English and Director of the Duke Press, after White's death in 1948.
Collection Overview
Collection centers around folklorist Frank Clyde Brown's papers related to his lifelong exploration and collecting of North Carolina and Appalachian folklore, which resulted in this vast archival collection of original folklore materials and editorial records for the project which published Brown's work in seven volumes as (The Frank C. Brown Collection of North Carolina Folklore, 1952-1964. Materials comprise about 1,049 tunes and songs recorded on wax cylinders and lacquer and aluminum phonodiscs, backup copies of the recordings on glass lacquer phonodiscs made by the Library of Congress in the 1940s, 30,000 written notes on lore, 650 musical scores, and numerous journal articles, student theses, books, lists, and other items. The folklore sources originated in at least 84 North Carolina counties, with about 5 percent from 20 other states and Canada, and came from the efforts of 650 other contributors besides Brown himself. Also included are the research notes and other papers of Charles Bond, a Duke graduate student who dealt with the collection in 1970.
Subjects range widely and include: ballads and songs (music as well as lyrics); European roots of North American folklore; folk music; folk poetry; games and parties; oral traditions and storytelling; superstitions; social conditions in the Southern States; African American traditions; work songs; and North American folklore in general. In addition, one can find rich resources on the study and teaching of folklore, and attitudes during the 1920s to 1950s about Southern customs and communities.
The collection is divided into the following series: Cylinders and Discs, which includes the Library of Congress glass lacquer phonodisc copies, Personal Papers, General Editors' Papers, Associate Editors' Papers, Charles Bond Research Material.
The Recordings Series includes 1,049 performances on original wax cylinders and phonodiscs, re-recordings of the cylinders and discs created by the Library of Congress in the 1940s, and supplementary materials. The original wax cylinders and phonodiscs were digitized and described as part of a CLIR/Mellon grant in 2015-2018.
The Personal Papers series includes Brown's correspondence, research files, and the extensive materials in the folklore collection, which include transcriptions and sheet music. All items were gathered by Brown, and taken over in 1943 by Dr. Newman Ivey White, who served as first general editor of the project from its inception then until his death in 1948. The General Editors' Papers include items which were related to and produced by the work of White, and Paull Franklin Baum who assumed duties at White's death, and saw the project through to its completion in 1964. The Associate Editors' Papers have been organized by editor, and include drafts and typescripts for various volumes.
The Charles Bond Research Material Series stems from the work of Charles Bond, a student of Professor Holger O. Nygard at Duke University. Bond opened the archival collection in 1970-1971, and prepared both an outline as well as a Tabulation of Unpublished Items in the collection. This series also includes correspondence, an index, and card files.
Related Materials
For further context, related materials and collections, see Frank Clyde Brown Recordings, a Guide to the Digital Collection
Existence and Location of Copies
Selected recordings from this collection have been digitized and are available in the Frank Clyde Brown Recordings - Duke Digital Collections
Ethnomusicology -- United States; Ethnomusicologists -- Correspondence; Folk literature -- Southern States; Folk music -- Southern States; Folk music -- United States; Folklore -- Appalachian region; Folklore -- North Carolina; Folklorists -- North Carolina; Superstition -- Southern States; Appalachian region -- Social life and customs; Appalachian region -- Music; North Carolina -- Social conditions; North Carolina -- Social life and customs; Cylinders (sound recordings); Digital audio formats; Tape reels; North Carolina Folklore Society; Brown, Frank Clyde, 1870-1943
- Cylinders and Discs, 10 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Digital copies of recordings are available via the links below. Original wax cylinder and phonodisc media are closed for playback but may be requested for visual inspection. Contact Rubenstein Library Research Services for further information.
  - Wax Cylinders, 1921-1935
    - RL00160-WC-0001, undated (Box 131, Audio-cylinder RL00160-WC-0001)
      Scope and Contents
      Recorded signal is extremely low or object has physically deteriorated to the point where content cannot be determined.
    - RL00160-WC-0002, 1921 (Box 131, Audio-cylinder RL00160-WC-0002)
      Track List
      Title: How I Love the Old Black Cat, performer: Strawbridge, Mary, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:37:628
      Title: The Broken Heart, performer: Strawbridge, Mary | Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:18:961
      Title: Farewell (You Are False), performer: Strawbridge, Mary, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:38:559
      Title: Seven Long Years I've Been Married, performer: Mansfield, Mamie, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:15:818
      Title: Charlie Brooks, performer: Strawbridge, Mary, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:19:413
      Title: Green Grows the Wild, performer: Nichols, Madge, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:38:490
      Title: What You Goin' to Do When the World's On Fire?, performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:39:881
      Title: It Blows and It Snows, performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:21:091
      Title: Old Molly Hare, performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:18:363
      Title: While the Southern Boys are Fighting, performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:38:252
      Title: When You Hear that Turtle Dove (If You Meet a Woman in the Morning), performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:17:102
      Title: Mississippi Lawyer [Jig No Words], performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:25:984
      Title: Bull In the Meadows (Run Sallie My Gal), performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:17:496
      Title: Bonnie Bess, performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:31:440
      Title: I Have No Mother Now, performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:34:248
      Title: The Drunkard's Lone Child, performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:45:038
      Title: The Old Ship of Zion, performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:24:686
      Title: The Fatal Wedding, performer: Robbins, Jewell, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:26:129
    - RL00160-WC-0003, 1921 (Box 131, Audio-cylinder RL00160-WC-0003)
      Title: The Scolding Wife, performer: Day, Ethel, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:31:616
      Title: Hard Times, performer: Webb, Pearle, location: Pineola (N.C.) | Avery County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:22:505
      Title: Paper of Pins (Little Lap Dog), performer: Webb, Pearle, location: Pineola (N.C.) | Avery County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:22:178
      Title: Granny, performer: Black, Ruth, location: Piney Creek (N.C.) | Alleghany County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:20:765
      Title: Jim, performer: Weaver, Lura, location: Piney Creek (N.C.) | Alleghany County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:52:654
      Title: The Letter that Never Came, performer: Black, Ruth, location: Piney Creek (N.C.) | Alleghany County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:39:702
      Title: unknown, performer: Holton, S.M., location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:45:542
      Title: Old Grimes (Old Grumbly is Dead), performer: Stroupe, Carrie, location: Lenoir (N.C.) | Caldwell County (N.C.), running time: 00:02:14:707
      Title: Old Time, performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:54:725
      Title: Faithful Friend, performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:42:003
    - RL00160-WC-0004, 1921-06-24 (Box 131, Audio-cylinder RL00160-WC-0004)
      Title: Pennsylvania Boy, performer: Weaver, Lura, location: Piney Creek (N.C.) | Alleghany County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:33:068
      Title: Goin' to Heaven With a Banjo, performer: Fletcher, Eula, location: Mabel (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:16:295
      Title: Sadie Ray, performer: Fletcher, Eula, location: Mabel (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:32:100
      Title: Red White and Blue, performer: McNeill, Hattie, location: Ferguson (N.C.) | Wilkes County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:29:160
      Title: Through the Woods, Through the Bushes, performer: Clarke, Eugenia, location: Collettsville (N.C.) | Caldwell County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:24:421
      Title: Sweetest Evelina, performer: Greer, I.G., location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:35:333
      Title: In the Baggage Couch Ahead, performer: Greer, I.G., location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:01:05:317
      Title: Battleship Maine, performer: Greer, I.G., location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:45:284
      Title: Raven Black Hair, performer: Greer, I.G., location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:37:295
      Title: The Sweet Trinity (Golden Willow Tree), performer: Greer, I.G., location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:01:00:092
      Title: The Jealous Lovers, performer: Greer, I.G., location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:22:484
      Title: The Blue Eyed Girl, performer: Greer, I.G., location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:14:687
      Title: The Broken Heart, performer: Greer, I.G., location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:24:976
      Title: Parting Words, performer: Greer, I.G., location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:39:735
    - RL00160-WC-0005, 1921 (Box 131, Audio-cylinder RL00160-WC-0005)
      Title: When I am Far Away Somewhere in France, performer: Moody, Birdie May, location: Shull's Mill (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:13:292
      Title: Tom Dula, performer: Moody, Birdie May, location: Shull's Mill (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:36:527
      Title: unknown, performer: Green, A.I., location: Heaton (N.C.) | Avery County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:22:296
      Title: unknown, performer: Green, A.I., location: Heaton (N.C.) | Avery County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:30:532
      Title: The Blind Child (The Blind Girl's Prayer), performer: Webb, Pearle, location: Pineola (N.C.) | Avery County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:22:508
      Title: Frog In the Meadow, performer: Webb, Pearle, location: Pineola (N.C.) | Avery County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:10:042
      Title: The Miller (The Jolly Miller), performer: McNeill, Hattie, location: Ferguson (N.C.) | Wilkes County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:10:670
      Title: The Weeping Willow (Willow Tree), performer: Lewis, Ethel, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:20:744
      Title: James Harris (The House Carpenter), performer: McNeill, Hattie, location: Ferguson (N.C.) | Wilkes County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:33:175
      Title: The Lonesome Pine, performer: McNeill, Hattie, location: Ferguson (N.C.) | Wilkes County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:29:221
      Title: I Came From Alabama, performer: McNeill?], Arron, location: Ferguson (N.C.) | Wilkes County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:33:024
      Title: Geordie (I'd Fight for the Life of Geordie), performer: McNeill, Hattie, location: Ferguson (N.C.) | Wilkes County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:25:645
      Title: unknown, performer: McNeill, Hattie, location: Ferguson (N.C.) | Wilkes County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:21:728
      Title: unknown, performer: Clarke, Eugenia, location: Collettsville (N.C.) | Caldwell County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:54:656
      Title: Three Leaves of Shamrock, performer: Clarke, Eugenia, location: Collettsville (N.C.) | Caldwell County (N.C.), running time: 00:01:52:807
    - RL00160-WC-0006, 1924 (Box 131, Audio-cylinder RL00160-WC-0006)
      Title: In a Cool Shady Nook (You, You, You), performer: Holton, Aura, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:29:822
      Title: No Sir (O Tell Me Why, O Tell Me Truly), performer: Holton, Aura, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:27:279
      Title: Mountain Dew (Down Under the Hill), performer: Holton, Aura, location: Durham (N.C.) | Durham County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:33:667
      Title: Springfield Mountain (Sarpint), performer: Poovey, W.E., location: Marion (N.C.) | McDowell County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:47:358
      Title: Sally Goodin (Jaybird and Sparrow), performer: Poovey, W.E., location: Marion (N.C.) | McDowell County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:20:141
      Title: Our Fathers They'll Be There, performer: Meyers, E., location: Concord (N.C.) | Cabarrus County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:57:500
      Title: Jesus Born in Bethlehem (Song of Jesus), performer: unknown, location: Concord (N.C.) | Cabarrus County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:30:007
      Title: Be Kind to a Stranger From Home, performer: unknown, location: unknown, running time: 00:03:47:548
    - RL00160-WC-0007, 1922-12-28/1922-12-29 (Box 131, Audio-cylinder RL00160-WC-0007)
      Title: The Passing Policeman, performer: Gallop, Theresa, location: Roanoke Island (N.C.) | Dare County (N.C.), running time: 00:01:52:543
      Title: In the Isle of St. Helena, performer: Tillett, C.K., location: Roanoke Island (N.C.) | Dare County (N.C.), running time: 00:01:06:509
      Title: Sallie Dover, performer: Tillett, C.K., location: Roanoke Island (N.C.) | Dare County (N.C.), running time: 00:01:02:969
      Title: The Sheffield Apprentice, performer: Tillett, C.K., location: Roanoke Island (N.C.) | Dare County (N.C.), running time: 00:01:06:320
      Title: The Maid I Left Behind, performer: Tillett, C.K., location: Roanoke Island (N.C.) | Dare County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:48:923
      Title: The Harmless Hare, performer: Tillett, C.K., location: Roanoke Island (N.C.) | Dare County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:55:973
      Title: Caroline of Edinburgh Town, performer: Tillett, C.K., location: Roanoke Island (N.C.) | Dare County (N.C.), running time: 00:01:12:496
    - RL00160-WC-0008, undated (Box 131, Audio-cylinder RL00160-WC-0008)
    - RL00160-WC-0009, 1922 (Box 131, Audio-cylinder RL00160-WC-0009)
      Title: Faithful Friend, performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:01:05:189
      Title: Sparking On a Sunday Night, performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:34:108
      Title: Home On the Range (Antelope Song), performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:50:494
      Title: unknown, performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:15:643
      Title: Rosa Lee the Prarie Flower, performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:44:433
      Title: Cold Mountain (or Gold Mountain), performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:51:196
      Title: Pretty Saro, performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:26:595
      Title: Morality, performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:27:982
      Title: Going to Heaven By the Light of the Moon, performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:22:049
      Title: Baptist, Baptist is My Name (Roll, Jordan, Roll), performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:37:823
      Title: Sweet Sunny South (Take Me Home), performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:47:334
      Title: The Dying Nun, performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:42:988
      Title: Lord Thomas and Fair Annet (Lord Thomas), performer: Cooke, Alice, location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:33:328
    - RL00160-WC-0010, undated (Box 131, Audio-cylinder RL00160-WC-0010)
      Title: Lamkin (Beaulampkins), performer: Smith, Thomas, location: Zionville (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:42:970
      Title: Singing the Ten Commandments, performer: Poole, I.T., location: Morganton (N.C.) | Burke County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:31:994
      Title: Jennie Jenkins, performer: Smith, Thomas, location: Zionville (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:38:775
      Title: Lord Thomas and Fair Annet (Lord Thomas), performer: Smith, Thomas, location: Zionville (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:20:905
      Title: unknown, performer: Hayman, L.D., location: Elizabeth City (N.C.) | Pasquotank County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:57:171
      Title: Sweet Lulur, performer: Greer, I.G., location: Boone (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:01:03:320
      Title: Sweet Bunch of Daisies, performer: Greer, I.G. | Smith, A., location: Vilas (N.C.) | Watauga County (N.C.), running time: 00:00:50:316
      Title: unknown, performer: Smith, Thomas | Norris, E.G. | Moir, location: unknown, running time: 00:00:37:146